"The Best Source and Dose of
Plant Sterols for Lowering Cholesterol"
Despite the vast literature
on phytosterols
lowering blood
cholesterol levels,
there is to date
no study investigating
the ultimate proof of efficacy:
the lowering of the incidence
of coronary heart disease.
This is probably the strongest
argument against them.
There are no studies
with hard endpoints
to confirm that the drop
in LDL cholesterol
from plant sterols translates
to a drop in heart attacks.
The reason is
that even if people start out
with a ten-year cardiovascular
disease risk of ten percent,
you'd have to randomize
about 30,000 people
to phytosterols for a decade
to detect such an effect.
And at a more reasonable
ten-year risk of five percent,
you might have to enroll
more than 300,000.
Now, one could argue
that the cholesterol lowering
is all we need to know,
since basically lowering
LDL cholesterol by any means
appears to lower
cardiovascular risk,
whether by statins,
other kinds of drugs,
diet, or surgery.
However, there was a big trial
of extended-release niacin
in a group of patients with LDLs
starting down in the low 60s,
and researchers saw
a further 10-point drop
after a few years
that should have dropped
the risk by at least 5 or 6%
but failed to offer
a statistically significant
benefit in the end.
So, there's at least one example
of that line of argument
failing.
There is that ezetimibe
that does have
a similar mechanism of action
as phytosterols—that is,
blocking cholesterol absorption.
It partially blocks the
cholesterol absorption receptor;
so, cholesterol absorption
is reduced by about 50%.
When it was put to the test,
it did indeed
significantly improve
cardiovascular outcomes.
And the 13-point drop in LDL
achieved by blocking
cholesterol absorption
with the drug is almost
the exact same drop in LDL
we'd expect from blocking
cholesterol absorption
with phytosterols,
based on more than 100
randomized controlled trials.
Does blocking
cholesterol absorption work
even if you don't eat
any cholesterol?
Yes, because the bulk
of the cholesterol
flowing through
our digestive tract
is dumped there
from our liver's own production.
It also works for those
on statin drugs.
In fact, adding two grams
of phytosterols a day
to your routine
may be equivalent
to like quadrupling
your statin dose.
So, if you are going
to try phytosterols
to lower your LDL level,
what's the best dose
and what's the best source?
The recommended daily dosing
is between
two to three grams a day,
based on dose-response curves
like this,
where the benefit
appears to plateau
at about those
two or three daily grams.
There's a comparable
benefit curve
with plant stanols
which are similar molecules.
Plant sterols and stanols
are absorbed better
if taken with meals,
because the maximum
cholesterol load
to the intestine occurs
after gallbladder contraction
and delivery
of cholesterol-rich bile
to the intestine.
Indeed, the same dose
of phytosterols
may have more than double
the LDL-lowering effect
when taken with meals
rather than between them
on an empty stomach.
The full
LDL-cholesterol-lowering effect
can be detected
after just two weeks
and may last
as long as you take them,
but as soon as you stop,
the cholesterol-lowering effect
will be lost
within a week or two.
Phytosterols
in those kinds of doses
are available in supplements
and in fortified foods,
which lower LDL equivalently.
As I talked about before,
the margarines
are a total non-starter.
Are there any healthy
phytosterol-fortified foods?
Not any that I could tell
where I live.
In Australia there's a plant
sterol-fortified shredded wheat,
but I don't know
if you can get it anywhere else.
That leaves us
with supplements.
It's always good to have
third-party certification
of authenticity,
though I think
there's only one
USP-certified brand
at the moment,
but ConsumerLab also tested
and approved three others.
They're also pretty expensive;
so, I was excited to see
that you can get it in bulk,
and you could presumably just
sprinkle a bit on your food,
but that presumption
may be wrong.
As a crystalline powder,
the free phytosterols
are much less efficient
at inhibiting cholesterol.
That's why the initial studies
a half century ago
were using doses of, like,
10 to 20 grams a day.
Then researchers figured out
how to make them more soluble
by making
fatty phytosterol esters,
which is what you see
in the capsules.
There are studies
suggesting that free sterols
block cholesterol absorption
as much as esterified sterols,
but they included equal parts
of an emulsifier
to improve absorption.
A study showing free sterols
could lower LDL
similarly relied
on some proprietary means
for solubilizing it.
Just for fun, I tried taking
the bulk powder for a month
and, indeed,
sadly saw zero effect,
whereas I got
a nice 17 point drop in LDL
taking the exact same dose
in encapsulated ester form.
Normally, I'm not a big fan
of lab tests,
but if you do start
phytosterol supplements,
I would get
your cholesterol tested before
and after a month or so
on them.
You should be able to get
your cholesterol tested
for free through your doctor,
but these days you can get
your cholesterol tested
at low cost or free
even without insurance
or a doctor visit.
While some individuals
respond immediately
and get a major shift
in lipid profiles,
others are much more resistant
or even completely insensitive
to plant sterols,
or do even worse.
Just because
the average response
is around a 10% drop
in LDL cholesterol,
maybe you'll be lucky
and respond even better.
These are all
individual patients,
and this first person
saw a 38% drop!
But it's also possible
you won't respond as well—
or, your cholesterol
may actually go up.
That unfortunate person
at the end
had a 33% increase in LDL;
so, even though
the average effect is good,
you want to make sure
it's actually working for you.